Finding Aid for the Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Records, 1926-1969 July MS.0423
University of Tennessee Libraries, Special Collections
Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Records
1926-1969 July
MS.0423
University of Tennessee Libraries, Special Collections
0.6 Linear feet
This collection consists primarily of bulletins, photographs, song sheets, member information, and other materials documenting the Smoky Mountains Hiking Club. Also included are a few issues of the Georgia Mountaineer, three guidebooks to various areas of the Smoky Mountains, and materials describing the building of a transmountain road in the 1960s and the passage of the 1964 Wilderness Bill.
Smoky Mountains Hiking Club of Knoxville.
Conditions Governing Access
Colletions are stored offsite, and a minimum of 24 hours is needed to retrieve these items for use. Researchers interested in consulting any of the collections are advised to contact Special Collections at special@utk.edu.
Acquisition Note
Laura E. and Ella Luttrell donated this collection to the Library between 1966 and 1969.
Biographical/Historical Note
The Smoky Mountains Hiking Club began in 1924 as an informal hiking program sponsored by the YMCA boys' camp in Gatlinburg, Tennessee. The link with the YMCA was severed when eligibility for membership was expanded and the club's numbers grew rapidly. Over the years, the Club has been active in establishing the Great Smoky Mountains National Park, performing Appalachian Trail maintenance, and promoting wilderness conservation in addition to organizing hikes and other outings in the Park.
Scope and Contents Note
This collection consists primarily of bulletins, photographs, song sheets, member information, and other materials documenting the Smoky Mountains Hiking Club. Also included are a few issues of the Georgia Mountaineer, three guidebooks to various areas of the Smoky Mountains, and materials describing the building of a transmountain road in the 1960s and the passage of the 1964 Wilderness Bill.
Arrangement
This collection consists of two boxes.
Subjects
Great Smoky Mountains (N.C. and Tenn.) -- Guidebooks.; Great Smoky Mountains (N.C. and Tenn.) -- History.; Great Smoky Mountains (N.C. and Tenn.) -- Pictorial works.; Great Smoky Mountains National Park (N.C. and Tenn.) -- Guidebooks.; Great Smoky Mountains National Park (N.C. and Tenn.) -- History.; Great Smoky Mountains National Park (N.C. and Tenn.) -- Pictorial works.
Container List
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Photographs, 1928 January 7-1931 May 3, undated (Box 1)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1947 March-May (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1950 May-December (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Bulletins, 1969 January-July (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Song Sheets and New Member Information, 1951 December 9-1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Fifth Annual Appalachian Trail Conference and Other Smoky Mountains Hiking Club Materials, 1926-1969 January, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Guide to the Southern Appalachians, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Outdoors in the Cumberlands Guidebook, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- A Preliminary Guide to the Greenbrier-Brushy Mountain Nature Trail Manuscript, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- The Georgia Mountaineer and Other National Park and Wilderness Materials, 1947 March 21-1967 February 15, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Transmountain Roads Proposal, Article, and Bulletins, 1967 February 15, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Wilderness Bill Articles and Bulletins, 1965-1968 August 30, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)